Paul James Wright

CONTACT INFORMATION Rm 614, Kelvin Building University of Glasgow Glasgow, G12 8QQ United Kingdom Work: +44 (0)14133 08855 Web: www.pauljwright.co.uk Email: paul.wright@glasgow.ac.uk Publication List: SAO/NASA ADS

RESEARCH INTERESTS My interests range from stellar to solar physics; my main interests lie in the heating of the solar atmosphere, including active regions and loops. I have expertise in the analysis of spectroscopic and narrowband Extreme Ultra-Violet (EUV) and X-ray data from the *SDO*, and *Hinode* satellites, in addition to the hard X-ray (HXR) imaging/spectroscopic observations from *NuSTAR*'s heliophysics campaign. Furthermore, I am currently investigating the modelling of coronal loop light-curves using the EBTEL (Enthalpy Based Thermal Evolution of Loops) hydrodynamic code with particular interest in the weak bremmstrahlung components, and the relevance for future soft to hard X-ray instruments and missions.

EDUCATION

University of Glasgow, Glasgow, UK

2014 – present (expected early 2018)

Ph.D. Solar Physics

Thesis Topic: *The Energetics of Small Flares and Brightenings* Advisers: Dr Iain G. Hannah, Dr Alexander MacKinnon

University of Southampton, Southampton, UK

2010 - 2014

MPhys Astrophysics with a year abroad

First-class honours (1:1) Adviser: Professor Malcolm Coe

Harvard University/Harvard-Smithsonian CfA, Cambridge, MA, USA

2013 - 2014

MPhys Astrophysics with a year abroad

Thesis Topic: Superflare Rates of Solar-Like Stars Advisers: Dr Steven H. Saar, Dr Jeremy J. Drake

CURRENT ACADEMIC APPOINTMENT

APPOINTMENTS

PREVIOUS ACADEMIC

Affiliate Staff Member, University of Glasgow SUPA School of Physics and Astronomy

2017 – present

Post-Graduate Research Assistant, University of Glasgow

2014 - 2017

SUPA School of Physics and Astronomy

Project: The Energetics of Small Flares and Brightenings

- Analysed observations of the Sun with *NuSTAR*, a telescope not designed for heliophysics. These observations are the most sensitive of their kind and have resulted in numerous, wide-ranging highly-collaborative peer-reviewed publications.
- Analysed non-flaring coronal time-series in pursuit of signatures of the coronal heating mechanism. Techniques included time-lag analysis (cross-correlation), Fourier analysis, wavelet analysis, and local intermittency measure (LIM).
- Studied the temperature distribution of the solar atmosphere through the recovery of an ill-posed inverse problem (the differential emission measure, DEM) using techniques such as Tikhonov regularisation, Markov-Chain Monte Carlo, and sparsity.
- The press-release image produced from the *NuSTAR* observations obtained for Wright *et al.* 2017 was published by numerous news outlets, and is one of the five iconic images from *NuSTAR*'s first five years in space.

Collaborators: Dr Iain Hannah, Dr Alexander MacKinnon

Visiting Researcher, NASA Goddard Space Flight Center (GSFC)

2016

Heliophysics Science Division

• Worked on the possibility of implementing DEM maps in the Helioviewer project, and their usefulness as an input for various established analysis techniques.

Collaborators: Dr Nicholeen Viall, Dr Jack Ireland

Research Scholar, Harvard-Smithsonian Center for Astrophysics (CfA)

2013 - 2014

Solar and Stellar X-Ray Group

- Designed and implemented a sophisticated stellar flare detection routine for long-cadence (30 mins) *Kepler* data obtained from a proprietary set of spectroscopically verified solar-type stars in three open clusters.
- A preliminary version of this work had coverage by Science, and The Smithsonian Magazine.

Collaborators: Dr Steven Saar, Dr Søren Meibom, Dr Jeremy Drake, Dr Vinay Kashyap

Paul James Wright

1 au James Wright			
PREVIOUS ACADEMIC	Summer Researcher, University of Southampton Astronomy Group	2013	
APPOINTMENTS (CONT.)	 Investigated the presence of double blue straggler sequences in globular cluste Space Telescope (WFC3) data. Collaborators: Dr Andrea Dieball 	rs using Hubble	
REFEREED JOURNAL PUBLICATIONS	[1] Marsh, A. J., Smith, D. M., Glesener, L. et al 2017. First NuSTAR Limits on Quiet Sun Hard X-Ray Transient Events, ApJ, 849, 131		
	[2] Wang, J., Simões, P. J. A., Jeffrey, N. L. S. et al 2017. Observations of Reconnection Flows in a Flare on The Solar Disk, ApJL, 847, L1		
	[3] Wright, P. J. , Hannah, I. G., Grefenstette, B. W., et al 2017. Microflare Heating of a Solar Active Region Observed with NuSTAR, Hinode/XRT, and SDO/AIA, ApJ, 844, 132		
	[4] Kuhar, M., Krucker, S., Hannah, I. G., et al 2017. Evidence of Significant Energy Phase of a Solar Flare from NuSTAR X-ray Observations, ApJ, 835, 6	Input in the Late	
FIRST AUTHOR	[5] Wright, P. J., Hannah, I. G., Viall, N. M., et al		
PUBLICATIONS IN PREPERATION	[6] Wright, P. J., Saar, S. H., Meibom, S., et al		
CONFERENCES, WORKSHOPS, & SCHOOLS	Invited Oral Presentations		
	ISSI Team Meeting: Coronal Nanoflares, Bern, CH Harvard-Smithsonian Center for Astrophysics, Cambridge, MA, USA	2016 2014	
	Oral/ePoster Presentations		
	Solar Physics Division Meeting (SPD/AAS), Portland, OR, USA	2017	
	Coronal Loops Workshop VIII, Palermo, Sicily, IT Living with a Star (SDO/LWS) Workshop, Burlington, VT, USA	2017 2016	
	Hinode 10, Nagoya, JP	2016	
	National Astronomy Meeting 2016, Nottingham, UK	2016	
	Hinode 9, Belfast, UK Glasgow-Cambridge Flare Workshop, Glasgow, UK	2015 2015	
	Poster Presentations		
	European Solar Physics Meeting (ESPM), Budapest, HU	2017	
	Solar Physics Division Meeting (SPD/AAS), Portland, OR, USA Living with a Star (SDO/LWS) Workshop, Burlington, VT, USA	2017 2016	
	Coronal Loops Workshop VII, Cambridge, UK	2015	
	NAM 2015, Llandudno, UK	2015	
	223rd AAS Meeting, National Harbor, MD, USA	2014	
	Schools Attended CESRA Radio Summer School 2015, Glasgow, UK	2015	
	STFC Advanced Summer School in Solar Physics, Dundee, UK	2014	
	Conferences/Workshops Attended		
	NuSTAR Heliophysics Workshop (remote participation), Berkeley, CA, USA SUPA Cormack Astronomy Meeting, Edinburgh, UK	2017 2015	
	RAS Discussion Meeting: Results from IRIS, London, UK	2015	
	SUPA Cormack Astronomy Meeting, Edinburgh, UK	2014	
	1st Space Glasgow Research Conference, Glasgow, UK	2014	
AWARDS AND	University of Glasgow		
GRANTS	Solar Physics Division Meeting (SPD/AAS) Student Poster Award	2017	
TOTAL: £7000	Solar Physics Division Meeting (SPD/AAS) Studentship Award	2017	
	Coronal Loops Workshop VIII Travel Award National Astronomical Observatory of Japan Travel Award	2017 2016	
	Hinode 9 Travel Award	2015	
	European Space Agency/Cambridge Philosophical Society Travel Award	2015	
	University of Southampton	2012	
	Research Scholarship Summer Studentship Grant	2013 2013	
	· · · · · · · · · · · · · · · · · · ·	-010	

Paul James Wright

More

INFORMATION

Gate, and GitHub.

TEACHING	University of Glasgow		
	Astronomy 1 Tutorial Demonstrator	2016 - 2017	
	Supervised students, and marked first-year astronomy problem sets.		
	Astronomy 3/4 (Honours) Laboratory Demonstrator	2015 - 2016	
	Demonstrated, supervised, and marked a number of final-year research projects covering topics such as asteroid light curves, and solar limb darkening.		
	Physics Pre-University Summer School	2015	
	Taught at a pre-university school for students entering first year.		
MEMBERSHIPS	NuSTAR Heliophysics Working Group, Member	2015 – present	
	International Space Science Institute (ISSI), Young Scientist Member	2015 – present	
	Member of Paola Testa's ISSI Team: New Diagnostics of Particle Acceleration Nanoflares from Chromospheric Observations and Modeling	in Solar Coronal	
	Royal Astronomical Society, RAS Fellow	2014 – present	
COMMUNITY	Nature Communications, Reviewer	2017 – present	
Involvement	Glasgow Astronomy & Astrophysics Group Meeting, Organiser	2017	
	CESRA Radio Summer School, Volunteer Organiser	2015	
SCIENTIFIC	Glasgow Science Centre, Demonstrator	2016	
OUTREACH	British Science Week, Demonstrator	2016	
	Institute of Physics: Women and Girls in Science, Demonstrator	2016	
	Scottish Television (STV), Guest Presenter	2015	
	World Wide Telescope, Ambassador	2013 - 2014	
	BBC Stargazing Live, Demonstrator	2013	
	So'ton Astrodome, Demonstrator	2012	
	BBC Bang Goes The Theory Roadshow, Demonstrator	2012	
	UK Solar Physics (UKSP) Nuggets , concise, easy-to-read science articles 84. The first <i>NuSTAR</i> microflare	2017	
	Hinode/XRT Picture of the Week (XPOW)		
	The First Microflare Observations with <i>Hinode/XRT & NuSTAR</i>	2017	
PERSONAL PROJECTS	ColourBlind, A repository for colour-blind-friendly colour tables.	Citations: 1	
PROFESSIONAL	Coursera, Inc. (MOOC Platform)		
DEVELOPMENT	Using Coursera.org, a massive open online course (MOOC) platform, to take specializations (a series of related courses and a final capstone project) offered by accredited universities to further develop skills and understanding in a wide range of computer science topics.		
	Data Science, Johns Hopkins University	2017 – present	
	Nine-course (plus capstone) introduction to data science. Mastering Software Development in R, Johns Hopkins University	2017 – present	
	Four-course (plus capstone) specialization providing riguourous training in R.		
	Statistics with R, Duke University	2017 – present	
	Four-course (plus capstone) specialization providing further training in R, with tics.	emphasis on statis-	
TECHNICAL SKILLS:	Computing: C, Python, R (caret, ggplot2, knitr), SQL, CRAN, IDL, LaTeX, git, GitHub, Hadoop (MapReduce, Spark, Pig, Hive), Linux/Unix, Mac OSX, Microsoft Windows, Bash, Microsoft Office, Adobe Creative Cloud, Keynote, Wordpress, Shiny, GoogleVis, and Plotly, HTML, CSS, Javascript		
	General: Data Analysis, Data Visualization, Interdisciplinary Collaboration, Public Speaking, Statistics, Teaching, Writing (Technical & Lay)		

More information and auxiliary documents can be found at http://www.pauljwright.co.uk, on Research-